Guide to the Hypes family papers, 1700s-2010 RL.00602
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hypes family papers
1700s-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hypes family
RL.00602
4 Linear Feet 6 boxes; 1 oversize folder; 1 pamphlet binder
Materials from the branch of the Hypes family that descended from Henry Hypes of Xenia, Ohio: Samuel Henry Hypes (1826-1916); his son, William Findlay Hypes; his grandson, Samuel Loomis Hypes; and his great-grandson, William P. Hypes. Collection includes a wide range of material from the Hypes family, particularly William Findlay Hypes, Samuel Loomis Hypes, and William P. Hypes. William Findlay Hypes' materials highlight his career at Marshall Fields and Co. of Chicago and his service as President of the Y.M.C.A. of Chicago, with emphasis on his family's world tour on behalf of the Y.M.C.A. in 1924-1925. Hundreds of postcards and photographs collected by the family are contained in the papers, including images from India, Ceylon (Sri Lanka), China, Europe, Egypt, and many more places, most unlabeled. Some material from Samuel Loomis Hypes' army service during World War I is also included, the most noteworthy being 24 black and white photographs featuring crowds awaiting the signing of the Treaty of Versailles and the shipping of troops back to the United States, including photographs of African American soldiers. Materials from William P. Hypes relate to his work with the Y.M.C.A. in the mid-twentieth century. The family's research into their genealogy and family history, unidentified family photographs, and smaller amounts of correspondence and material from other family members are also included.
Approximately 2250 Items
Biographical and Historical Note
The branch of the Hypes family documented in this collection descended from Nicholas Hipes, a cabinet maker who emigrated from Oberstein, Germany, in 1750. Following his first wife's death at sea, Hipes re-married in Philadelphia and settled with his second wife in Virginia. The couple had three sons, including Henry Hipes, who later changed his name to Hypes following a disagreement with his oldest brother, Peter Hipes. Peter apparently mismanaged the family's land and finances following Nicholas' death, so angering his brothers Henry and John that they changed their names to Hypes.
Henry Hypes and his wife, Patience Reynolds, were married on March 12, 1795, and lived in Virginia. Following a camp meeting, the couple converted to Methodism, freed their slaves, and were subsequently driven out of their Virginia neighborhood by their slave-holding neighbors. In 1811, they moved to Xenia, Ohio, with their children. Patience died in 1823, and Henry re-married the following year. His oldest daughter by his first marriage, Nancy Hypes, married Nathan Horner in Ohio. In 1824, the Horners settled in Lebanon, Illinois, where they ran a mill and general store. Nancy's brother, Benjamin Hypes, soon joined them there and eventually bought out the store.
Henry Hypes also fathered Samuel Henry Hypes, who was born on September 25, 1825, in Xenia, Ohio. Samuel Henry grew up in Xenia and also spent several years clerking for his brother, Benjamin, in Lebanon. While in Lebanon he met Hannah Van Brocklin, a teacher; they married in Oneida, N.Y., on December 31, 1856, and settled permanently in Xenia. Samuel Henry and Hannah Hypes had six children: Henry Martin Hypes (1858-1868); Oran F. Hypes (a senator, d. 1915); William Findlay Hypes; Lincoln R. Hypes; Mrs. William L. McCague; and Carrie Hypes.
Samuel Henry Hypes was a store clerk in Xenia. During the Civil War he traveled to Shiloh and Vicksburg as a photographer, returning to Ohio in 1863. He also served as assistant postmaster of Xenia until the 1870s. In 1872, he entered the insurance business, eventually founding a fire and real estate insurance company. Hannah Hypes died in 1916; Samuel Henry Hypes died in 1917.
Their son William Findlay Hypes moved to Chicago in 1880 and was the general sales manager of the wholesale house of Marshall Field and Co. for over thirty years. Hypes also served as president of the Chicago Y.M.C.A., president of the Union League Club in 1915, and was the first president of the North Shore Musical Festival Association. In 1924, he left with his wife on a nine-month world tour on behalf of the Y.M.C.A. The couple traveled to Y.M.C.A. centers in Japan, China, Manila, Korea, India, Ceylon (Sri Lanka), Palestine, Greece, Turkey, Egypt, and Europe.
William Findlay Hypes had at least three children: Muriel, Samuel Loomis, and Ruth. Samuel Loomis Hypes was a captain the U.S. Army's 803rd Pioneer Infantry during World War I. Following the war, he was a purchasing agent for Marshall Field and Co., and later became President of the Weiboldt Stores of Chicago. He and his wife, Charlotte Hypes, moved to Fairview, North Carolina, and started the Sugar Hollow Development Co. in 1953.
Samuel Loomis Hypes' son, William P. Hypes, also worked for the Y.M.C.A. in the 1960s and 1970s. Several files from his work are present in this collection.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, negatives are closed to use; corresponding prints and digital copies available.
Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
Provenance
The Hypes family papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007, 2011, 2013, and as a purchase in 2018.
Collection Overview
There is a wide range of material from the Hypes family's many generations present in this collection. Some early material exists from Henry Hypes, including an inventory of his property upon his death, and some correspondence from relatives. Other early materials include family photographs, which are largely unlabeled and undated but include formats such as tintypes, a daguerreotype, cartes de visite, negatives, and others.
The Hypes' attempts to reconstruct their family tree resulted in several letters between extended family members and distant cousins, as well as genealogical maps and notes, dating from the early to mid-twentieth century.
The majority of the collection dates from William Findlay Hypes and his family. W.F. Hypes' materials include correspondence and clippings about his career with Marshall Fields and Co., as well as news coverage of his world tour on behalf of the Y.M.C.A. from 1924 to 1925. The collection also contains photographic prints, negatives, and postcards from this trip, featuring images from India, China, Japan, Egypt, Ceylon (Sri Lanka), Europe, and other unidentified places. The photographs are largely gelatin silver prints, and many have silvering. The majority of photographs are amateur shots presumably taken by the Hypes family. However, there are several sets of images which were clearly purchased by W.F. Hypes or other family members as travel souvenirs, including a set from India taken by H.R. Ferger and a set from Taormina, Italy. These all appear to date from the early 1900s. Many types of postcards are present, including real photo postcards and tinted color postcards. Several postcard books were purchased as souvenirs. Most postcards have been sorted by location; real photo postcards have also been sleeved to better protect the images. Real photo postcard locations include Norway, Manila, China, Japan, and a set from the Canadian Rockies.
An earlier trip to Europe and the Middle East by W.F. Hypes and his wife is described in letters between them and their daughter Muriel. This trip appears to have been taken in May and June, 1910. Since most of the collection's photographs are undated, some could date from this trip instead of the world tour trip from 1924-1925.
One part of the collection is closed to researchers: there is a small amount of nitrate and safety negatives. These appear to be taken by W.F. Hypes, and include family photographs, scenes from Jamaica, and scenes of a tiger hunt during the Hypes' Y.M.C.A. tour. The tiger hunt images are available as prints in the photographs portion of the materials. All negatives are closed to researchers.
Along with the extensive amount of photographs and postcards, W.F. Hypes' portion of the papers includes souvenir booklets and other collectibles from his travels. Also present are materials from the World's Fair in Chicago in 1893, including a set of tickets as well as a stock certificate. Hypes' political leanings can be inferred from a Republican National Convention ticket for the 1904 election, as well as a small, movable medal that spins and denounces William Jennings Bryan.
Another noteworthy part of the collection comes from Samuel Loomis Hypes, W.F. Hypes' son, who served as a captain in the U.S. Army's 803rd Pioneer Infantry during World War I. This portion of the papers contains 24 black-and-white photographs (18? June-19 July 1919) featuring crowds awaiting the signing of the Treaty of Versailles and the shipping of troops back to the United States. Photographs often have captions in white ink. There are six crowd scenes in Paris and outside Versailles before and after the signing of the treaty. However, the majority of the photographs follow the movement of ships and troops out of Brest Navy yard, including the USS Imperator and the USS Philippine. There are group photos of the 803rd's officers and one photograph of a German submarine. Among the 4,000 troops aboard the Philippine were many African American soldiers, and there are photographs of these men playing in the 803rd's regimental band and of a boxing match they held during the voyage, as well as other photos. The collection also contains two postcards showing group photographs of soldiers [officers?] taken at Plattsburgh, N.Y., in 1916 - probably at the large World War I military training camp there.
Other materials from Samuel Loomis Hypes include his officer's record book, honorary discharge following the war, as well as clippings about Sugar Hollow, a North Carolina development begun by Hypes and his wife in the 1950s.
Finally, the collection also includes several files from William P. Hypes, an officer in the Y.M.C.A. in the 1960s and 1970s, particularly from his work towards the Y.M.C.A. World Action program.
African American soldiers -- History -- 20th century; Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); Treaty of Versailles (1919); Treaty of Versailles (1919) -- Pictorial works; Voyages around the world -- 20th century; World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, African American; World War, 1914-1918 -- Peace; World War, 1914-1918 -- Pictorial works; Brest (France) -- History; Versailles (France); Xenia (Ohio); Black-and-white photographs; Cellulose nitrate film; Daguerreotypes (photographs); Negatives (photographs); Postcards; Tintypes (prints); Hypes, Ruth; Hypes, Henry; Hypes, William Findlay; Hypes, Samuel Loomis, 1894-1963; Marshall Field's (Department store); Hypes, William P.; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 803rd -- History; United States. Army -- African American troops -- History -- 20th century; Hypes family; USS Philippine (Ship); World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.); United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 803rd -- Pictorial works; USS Imperator (Ship); Young Men's Christian Association (Chicago, Ill.)
- Hypes Family Papers, 1700s-1969, 5 boxes, 1 folder
  - Correspondence re: Hypes genealogy/family history (Box 1)
  - Hypes genealogy/family history (Box 1)
  - Wright family genealogy (Box 1)
  - Unidentified family photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Family photographs, undated (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    4 tintypes and 1 daguerreotype (possibly Samuel H. Hypes).
  - Henry Hypes
    - Letters, personal inventory, and family tree, 1700s-1850 (Box 1)
  - Fanny Hypes
    - Daughters of the American Revolution application materials, 1908 (Box 1)
  - Samuel H. Hypes
    - Outgoing correspondence to his son, William Findlay Hypes, 1910-1915 (Box 1)
    - Obituary, 1917 (Box 1)
  - William Findlay Hypes
    Conditions Governing Access
    Negatives are closed to use. Corresponding photographic prints for all the negatives and digital copies of the 5 nitrate negatives are available.
    - World's Columbian Exposition materials, Chicago, 1893 (Box 1)
      A set of tickets to the exposition as well as a certificate for one share of capital stock.
    - Materials (Box 1)
      Republican National Convention ticket, 1904; Pro-McKinley medal, 1904; Diary, 1929; other small papers.
    - Correspondence between Mrs. Hypes and her children, Samuel Loomis and Muriel Hypes, 1910 (Box 1)
      During the Hypes' travels through Europe, 1910
    - Marshall Field and Co. correspondence and clippings, 1900s-1925 (Box 1)
      Includes an index of travelling salesmen kept by Hypes.
    - Y.M.C.A. correspondence and clippings, 1917-1923 (Box 2)
    - Y.M.C.A. world tour clippings from Asia, 1924-1925 (Box 2)
    - Travelling souvenirs, 1910-1925 and undated (Box 2)
    - Y.M.C.A. and Marshall Field and Co. clippings, 1924-1933 (Box 2)
    - Y.M.C.A. world tour photographs, 1924-1925, 4 folders (Box 2)
      Many photographs are unlabeled and undated. Places documented include Gibraltar, Italy, China, Ceylon (Sri Lanka), India, and Egypt.
    - A Memoir of Egypt photo album, 1925 (Box 8)
      Scope and Contents
      Presented to W.F. Hypes by central Y.M.C.A. staff in Cairo, Egypt.
    - Postcards with real photographs
      - Canada (Box 2)
      - China and Hong Kong (Box 2)
      - Columbia River, Oregon (Box 3)
      - India (Box 3)
      - Italy and France (Box 3)
      - Japan (Box 3)
      - Jerusalem and Palestine (Box 3)
      - Manila (Box 3)
      - Norway (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 3)
    - Professional photograph sets
      - India, taken by H.R. Ferger, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Canadian Rockies (Box 3)
      - Taormina, Italy (Box 3)
      - Japan (tinted photographs) (Box 3)
    - Postcards (Box 4)
      A wide variety of postcards from a wide variety of places, largely undated. Includes both color and black-and-white images. Some contain correspondence, but the majority are blank and appear to have been collected as souvenirs from W.F. Hypes' family travels. Also includes some postcard books. Postcards have been sorted by location into envelopes within the box.
      - Assorted places (Box 4)
      - Belgium (Box 4)
      - Ceylon (Sri Lanka) (Box 4)
      - China (Box 4)
      - England (Box 4)
      - France, 3 packets (Box 4)
      - India, 2 packets (Box 4)
      - Italy, 2 packets (Box 4)
      - Japan, 2 packets (Box 4)
      - Manila (Box 4)
      - Palestine/Jerusalem (Box 4)
      - Spain (Box 4)
      - United States, 6 packets (Box 4)
    - Photographic safety negatives, Jamaica? (closed), circa 1938; 31 items 1 box 1 original processing envelope; 30 safety negatives (Box 6)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Negatives are closed to use. Prints from this trip are available in the collection.
    - Nitrate negatives, riding on elephant (during tiger hunt, India?), circa 1920s; 8 items 1 pam binder nitrate negatives negatives approximately 2 1/2 x 4 1/2 inches (Folder 1)
      Nitrate negatives are closed to use. Corresponding prints available; slated for digitization.
  - Samuel Loomis Hypes
    - Photographs, record book, and U.S. Army discharge from World War I, 1916-1919 (Box 3)
      Comprises primarily 24 black-and-white photographs (18? June - 19 July 1919) featuring crowds awaiting the signing of the Treaty of Versailles and the shipping of troops back to the United States. Photographs often have captions in white ink. There are 6 crowd scenes in Paris before and outside Versailles before and after the signing of the treaty. However, the majority of the photographs follow the movement of ships and troops out of Brest Navy yard, including the USS Imperator and the USS Philippine. There are group photos of the 803rd's officers and one photograph of a German submarine. Among the 4,000 troops aboard the Philippine were many African-American soldiers, and there are photographs of these men playing in the 803rd's regimental band and of a boxing match they held during the voyage, as well as other photos. The collection also contains two postcards showing group photographs of soldiers [officers?] taken at Plattsburg, N.Y.[?], in 1916.
    - Officer's record book, 1918 (Box 3)
    - Sugar Hollow, NC, printed materials, 1980s (Box 3)
    - Sugar Hollow, NC, clippings, 1950s-1980s (Box 3)
    - Certificate of appreciation (Oversize-folder 1)
  - William P. Hypes
    - Y.M.C.A. planning, 1969-1970s (Box 3)
    - Y.M.C.A. World Action, 1970s (Box 5)
    - Y.M.C.A. International correspondence, 1967-1981 (Box 5)
    - Y.M.C.A. Summary reports (Box 5)
    - Y.M.C.A. St. Louis consultation, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Y.M.C.A. St. Louis consultation follow-up, 1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Ruth Hypes
    - Correspondence, 1975-2010 and undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Unidentified or undated materials (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Oversize (Oversize-folder 1)